software engineering radio episode 13
rubian practice
welcome this is the sequel to our
episode on scripting languages in that
episode we promised to have a second
episode on this topic more specifically
on Ruby and so here in this episode alex
interviews tom class thomas originally a
java enterprise developer and in this
episode he talks to us about his
experiences with his first ruby project
hi Tom could you please introduce
yourself bill hey Alex
I'm Java developer and usually I have my
clients developing enterprise systems
enterprise applications so how did you
get to me I was looking for an
alternative to Java and I was scanning
the scene and found Perl
type Ruby and all those kind of like
scripting languages and it just jumped
into Ruby because I tried a few others
of them before and you know kind of was
like disappointed from some and others
were like too complex so I gave Ruby
[Music]
prior experience with Ruby or was this
the first time you can contact away okay
so about two years ago I had to develop
a application for a client and in order
to do that we had to provide a prototype
so within a timeframe of about two weeks
we had to develop a rather complex state
machine UI interface and database
connectors and stuff we wouldn't want to
implement it in Java because would be
too slow and too complex and we looked
for a scripting language so we decided
to use Ruby because we had up everything
that we needed like ER be embedded Ruby
hard for the UI interface we had my
sequel connectors and stuff so we
started as Krypton okay two weeks is a
pretty tough schedule I would say
that's all if you don't know the
language you have no prior experience
how did you start with Ruby I mean it's
a new language you have any framework so
all technologies new that's what's a
huge thing to learn I guess
so we picked the most famous book that
we could find at that point and that was
a big X book by the pragmatic
programmers you know just by reading
chapter by chapter and going for the
examples we just were able within a few
hours or actually two days or something
to build up the basics of the
application and then learn more and
applied it and within two weeks we could
deliver that prototype and that was like
pretty amazing I think so two years what
was your first impression of you will be
how does it look like if you have no
prior weeks experience given that I have
a strong Java background and I was also
working on Perl projects a little bit of
Python which I never got into my brains
for some reason like for an old program
it like they look pretty familiar from
the beginning and it wasn't actually
hard to to understand the syntax and it
wasn't quite complex to understand the
standard library that comes with Ruby
yeah so so huge at least not as huge
others Java stuff or not yet they all
say well I mean if you look at the item
world they have lots of libraries and
actually I envy you a little bit about
that but you know there is a lot of
things that are coming up for Ruby and
you can be really productive like in no
time mmm so coming back to the book yeah
we learned Ruby by the book basically so
that movie is also yeah object-oriented
from core was a thing you did like a lot
and it helped you to get into what were
the other things okay I guess I like the
syntactical sugar that comes with Ruby
like you know closures or they call it
blocks and
the very simple syntax like which is
very reduced to what you actually need
and if you if you need more you simply
define in Ruby that's a beaut about the
whole thing so if you think in
domain-specific languages or something
it's very easy to define your own
keywords and your own concept and embed
it into the language now that's pretty
different from Java I think I never I
have no prior Smalltalk experience so
this was the first language to me that
had this embedded into the language this
yes strong emphasis on building your own
language within the language pretty cool
thing I think yeah
would you say Ruby's pretty major I mean
you did the whole project in two weeks
had the first prototype working it
sounds like it just works I mean there
are not so many commercial projects out
there so a lot of people I guess Arbit
worried about the state Ruby they'd
never heard before from Ruby they who
hear from c-sharp and Chava all the time
but never from Ruby how would you rate
movie what I think Ruby has a lot of
momentum since the appearance of braids
and a lot of people are jumping on that
train so I guess Ruby itself will mature
from this or you know benefit from this
process yeah having been said currently
we're in the process of of a you Ruby
language upgrade so people will still
modify the language and with the tool of
2.0 version of Ruby will face a lot of
changes there I mean chances are that
your old programs will continue working
with the 1.8 version ok the 2.0 version
of Ruby is a
as I understand you do you think I mean
this is a pretty interesting point we
have languages that very slow languages
that really get to get you job dates in
a short period of time what do you think
is better to have this steady but slow
progression or a bit more yeah
aggressive language progression I think
it's good for OB to actually evolve and
even at the cost of change and
incompatibility with all the programs
because it will definitely be a clean up
you know a 1.8 is around for a bunch of
years now we have we had 106 before and
you know probably the time for change
the language designers learned a lot and
instead of like carrying with us all the
stuff that was building earlier on maybe
just make sense to cut it often and
continue with the French base ok so
let's set would you recommend Ruby in
any project situation or is it really
more of prototyping language or whatever
well I see different applications for it
one would definitely be as rails already
proved as possible to work with Ruby in
that area web application yes okay so
you have the full cycle of support from
database to the web UI you can apply the
model-view-controller content and this
is probably all you need them or you
ever need for a web application so
that's fine
we're also would use Ruby is in the
native or say rich client programming
model oh so I wouldn't really go for
Java C sharp or
other languages but really use Ruby or
Python or alive okay or the application
that's pretty strange i I never sort of
ruby has a GUI client which line
whatever language I mean the I I hope
this is not too much flame babe and the
UI frameworks I know for Ruby I don't
really have the Ruby feeling to me
lately or mostly seem to be part of some
framework that already exists into the
space but they are not that dynamic and
will be feeling so I would never I would
never get the idea of doing a UI
development to through we right now
mm-hmm
yeah I can get I can understand that
point but you have two options the one
option is the platform independent way
of developing Ruby you eyes and then
will probably lead you to some kind of
framework that you just mentioned and I
would follow that track because you lose
a lot of native feeling on certain
platforms so a second option will be to
use the language connectors to the
specific windowing tool and in the case
of gnome or KDE that would be like
really native adapters work and use the
widget set off the off the platform and
that works pretty well is there's an
application out there called Alexandria
if I remember correctly it's a library
manager and it is it's being deployed
with a Windows toolkit adapter and they
I guess it's always ten mm-hmm adapter
and it feels natively so you can you can
you cannot tell that it's a ruby
application it behaves natively pretty
interesting to Roman and you know the
big benefit will be of course the the
speed of the development yes so instead
of having the traditional build compile
link whatever cycle it is
sorry I mean today there are even people
out there that still you see or C++ or
you eyes and it's just too much work in
my opinion okay so given your prior
experience with Shawa what would you
still use Travers stuff you you would do
with Java anymore or yeah definitely the
systems that I develop on a daily basis
they usually are more complex in web
applications or native user interfaces
they work together with transaction
monitors they need whatever kind of
protocol whatever is to be monitored
like in the enterprise service world
world
I don't think you really have a
replacement for Joey if you think about
so that is sad I still think there is a
possibility to combine both and for
example use Ruby for a web UI and for a
simple database access and use whatever
kind of remote service avión to forward
or to delegate operations to a say more
complex system that involves messaging
like complex transactional behavior
something that's currently missing from
hmm okay and I heard the two this stuff
gets more yes
beat again because it was quiet for a
while in between but scanning speed
again
so maybe yeah that's another chance
there to combine and travel more for the
developers of our listeners could you
describe some Ruby features that Sharma
doesn't have or that yeah you'd like
very much and think Java developers
should know
[Music]
what I usually do when I program ruby is
a technique called duck typing mm-hmm
though the point about duck typing is
that a object doesn't have to belong to
a certain type in order to implement
functionality that you want to use as a
programmer so for example in Java you
have to implement interfaces or extender
to super classes in order to get the
functionality that you defined somewhere
else in the type hierarchy in Ruby you
don't have to do that and the duck
typing technique just enables the
programmer to you know take whatever
object and pass it into some kind of
method and if the method accepts that
there is just some kind of other method
it's getting complicated it needs a
certain functionality from this object
just being passed and you just involved
not typically not paying attention to
whatever kind of type are you know since
we don't have a static compilation step
in between the interpreter is fine just
accepting the object and of course you
might end up with the wrong time
exception but it's up to the programmer
to manage that and this is really I
don't know how to explain it it feels
pretty strange from a child programmers
perspective I know this from objective-c
or for example and it's so great it's
such a huge leap and it sounds like a
heck because if it isn't whatever check
our subclass on the object why should
the method be able to deal with it when
there are so many situations where you
can use it and you would have to define
hundreds of interfaces in Java to mimic
the same thing and of course you
for example to for print line or
whatever for every method defined
interface but you don't want to of
course you know you have thousands of
interfaces flying around and get a very
complex system yes I like this typing
thing exactly I mean this is how the
Ruby people build up the standard
library so you just in your regular
logic you just pass in a Airy and you
use the shift operator to add new
elements here and maybe another use for
this very same operation will be to pass
in a file and the shift operator will
depend the data to the file yeah without
any change in the code so that's
beautiful yeah great other things what I
also like is mixing I use make sense
before in languages like Objective C
which had a close connection to small
talk and of course the small of people
knew everything but you know that's
something I really missed in the Java
world where you can define your a lot of
functionality and then just imported as
they mix in again we have in Java we
have this inheritance problem hmm
in order to overcome this inheritance
thing you have to use delegation and
Java doesn't even have a say great
supporting or delegation model I wish
they would have a delegated keyboard
just say well those interface methods
that I just an area they go to this
delegation object but instead I have to
add like every single method that I want
to delegate to another one so just just
to explain it a bit deeper mix-ins our
code you can like I can basically what I
do is I define in Ruby a module and
implement and it has some kind of
implementation on the logic that I just
want to share with other objects so for
example say simple example is logging
right yeah so we have like the typical
info fatal war
Eero whatever methods and instead of
three implementing yet or instead of
like for example if you decide to this
is an option for you instead of
delegating it you just mix in those
methods into the object that you're that
were just talking about and then you're
fine to use those methods as if they
would belong to the very implementation
of that object that you yeah it's a bit
clean of a multiple inheritance I mean
in C class possibly we often use
multiple inheritance to simulate it and
we didn't really have real is our
relationships to to the base classes but
we needed to import some code to don't
write it's a few times where to delegate
whatever so multiple inheritance was
often a not so nice heck to get to
things make sense to pretty clean I
think all right fortunately not a lot of
people asked me to program C to us from
that segment you can see my direction
yeah okay same few things on the meta
programming model uh I think that's also
very different from the travel world
okay so the funny thing is and I
mentioned that before with the DSL
domain-specific languages it's very easy
to extend the Ruby language by your own
keywords concept we usually you do this
using media program and that means you
extend classes during runtime with
additional behavior how would you do
that that's pretty magical there's some
kind of very complex internal mechanism
so Ruby where you that you probably have
to understand before you want to jump
into that because it has to do with
visibility of instance variables and
methods and all the kind of thing but in
the code itself it comes down to
applying the shift operator to a class
and then defining your methods and they
will append it to exactly this class at
university fine now that's great I mean
you can really add the runtime extent
classes single objects it's even a new
method tuned to an object I mean that's
very straight from the Java perspective
again so pretty dynamic pretty powerful
but also of course you can vary this way
should be seven and Eve if you don't
know what to do but I don't have the
feeling right now that it's really that
huge problem and in practice what I
think as long as developers know what
you're what they are doing and what are
your hands for that's fine and you know
probably the one example that that
really struck me was the in rails you
have due to the media programming
mechanism basic standard the integer
type so that you can say for dogs days
from now
yeah and I was looking up the standard
library as well you know what's
happening so I had to jump into the
rails documentation and see well they
have exactly that class definition it
extends the integer class yeah so and
obviously they're not modifying the
standard library on your hard disk on
your local machine but they doing that
during runtime yeah so the possibilities
are yeah also has a dark side within it
I mean it's always or it could at least
be hard to read or understand the Ruby
program a few you are able to modify
everything that's they are you have
almost adorned my mind the program
you're working in so it's a different
thing I guess I'm not sure if we or how
we fix this with documentation and stuff
like that I mean the more complex and
the more people are working on such a
project
the Harley this might get untrue on this
I think it's always a two-stage problem
because we have the frame
developers don't really have to provide
that functionality and of course they
have to understand the language
mechanism just what I said about
visibility and stuff and extensions and
then as a say application programmer say
you want to develop a race application
you don't have to understand that you
have to use it or you can't and you know
it's good met little names are there I
guess so and the second thing of course
we come back to the to unit has rails
for example has a whole infrastructure
set up to support the programmer you
know in order to unit test the
application and you know doing
test-driven development all day in the
Java world I wouldn't start programming
Ruby without tests anyway you know I can
see there is even more need with those
dynamic languages here to unit test the
application on a more thorough basis
yeah it's also interesting I think we
get more to the thing small talk at
where the the strong separation between
language and framework and or runtime
environment gets more fuzzy I mean
Ruby's as you said it's framework
language runtime it's all more dependent
on each other therefore more powerful
strength should see how we get back to
the basics for small talk yeah okay so
after done this project or prototype and
project I guess ruby has also some
programs and there are some
disadvantages of the problems cave it's
whatever could you give us a few
examples where should we take care not
to do some problems whatever okay so as
a Java programmer I'm really working
with II's today that support my same
working style
more efficiently than than used before
say we have refactorings we have all
these kind of things that simplified a
little programmer I don't have this rule
and that's what I'm missing most so I
have to go back to using VI on whatever
kind of editor and some people are using
this text making is really adapted
towards Ruby there's lots of support for
Ruby programs in there I can't really
touch on it because I never used it
before but that's missing and I I want
to have refactoring and I want to have
maybe like quick navigation within
classes and then on navigation on the
file store so if you're willing to
accept those disadvantages well I mean
then I guess we will definitely be a new
thing that that's worth looking hmm the
other thing is and I mention it before
we'll be still moving so if you decide
today that you want to do a rails app
and you of course have to make it work
on the current stable tree and that
means the 1.8 version of Ruby then you
have to be prepared to you know have a
whole bunch of legacy running for years
or at some point cut the 1.8 off and
like migrate your application and nobody
at this point can tell how much work
that would be yeah so let me have a few
words to the IDE stuff I mentioned it in
our first scripting language episode we
got some feedback on the yeah
refactoring topic especially and a lot
of people said you can't do refactoring
without static typing which is not true
in my opinion for example the first very
first reflection browser was actually a
smaller browser so it has to work
somehow the point is you have to
implement your effective browser
completely different you you can
build it up on the static type until you
have there's a lot of things you have to
do a grand time run time inspection soup
for example renaming a method is
implemented in smarter browser they
renamed the method actually and
implement another method with the same
name as the old one to catch all the
cause from the clients and that's the
way they they can find out who is
calling this method and then at runtime
edit the corners so it's it's completely
different how to implement it you have
to shift a few things from compile time
which is not very of course to run time
but it also you have possibilities you
don't have with child or baby because
you every time you have to work with an
object just create one and ask it for it
so you don't have to rely on type info
you can just ask you client or whatever
check in for the information you need so
it's definitely possible to to build a
vector in browser for me it's hard to
say they are more powerful or less
powerful than the refactorings browser
we know from the static type languages
and this static versus dynamic thing is
not the only criteria and I mean look at
C++ we still have no real good
properties I don't know of a really good
refactoring browser because of all these
dot H files and the complex syntax and
then and precompiled stuff so it's a
different thing it has to be implemented
different but I'm pretty sure we'll see
go through factoring browser's whoo it's
just a matter of time but back to my
initial question I always have the
feeling that Ruby is a bit how should I
say redundantly defined there are a lot
of things how to write a loop I don't
know I've never
there are many many ways how to write a
simple loop you can use an integer and
the times metal method for in and a lot
of things are redundant li defined so
that I didn't like that so much how
how's your feeling on this if you refer
to Y limbs and unless basically most of
the time you're using the same loop
construct session using Google languages
but sometimes I see it's nice that I can
write any in in a very simple way using
an unless or something it makes it may
be a bit more complicated on maybe more
unusual on the first glance but you know
I I don't have a problem with that okay
any other thing we should consider with
when you work with Ruby so if you're not
working on a server-side and you have to
deploy your code basically to a customer
and school then you might have a problem
because Ruby doesn't allow you to
generate some kind of byte code the way
- dirty well as a consequence your
clients have access to your sauce boom
well they can read whatever kind of
intellectual property you put in there
you know and well at this time I prefer
developing service applications using
will be and and web view eyes and stuff
and not actually delivering rich client
so to my customers sure it's so option
skating wouldn't work of course with
Ruby I mean you can could remain and
rename the names of a methods but still
it's there so it's not so right so smart
people will always be obviously the code
yeah I think currently there is an
effort and to generate C code from Ruby
advantages to notice so that probably
means that you can run the Ruby to see
generate a compile your application soon
and then
you know that's something you can
deliver Wow however they do all the
dynamic stuff well that's okay
so let's sum it up what are the few
highlights key points you would sum up
to her own business
I'd say Ruby works very well in real
project situations where you can keep
your source code on the server side and
where your applications are not as
complex as what you would solve with
Java Enterprise Systems that said I want
to connect groovy applications ideally
with the Java world to get benefits of
both you know it's it's a good
opportunity to learn about new concepts
like maybe changes your view on what
you're currently doing on a daily basis
and I just recommend to look into okay
fine
thanks a lot for this view Thanks
[Music]
this was another episode of software
engineering radio the software
engineering radio team wants to thank
Henning poly for providing the music as
well as lips and comm for hosting in
bandwidth for more information on the
podcast past episodes and feedback go to
s e - radio dotnet
[Music]